So today's דף daf is עין א, Ayin Aleph, 71, and we
pick up at the bottom of עין עמוד ב Ayin Amud Bet
and we are discussing the whole status of the קרבן חגיגה Korban
Chagigah and we have seen the position of בן תימא Ben Tema
that says the חגיגה Chagigah is pretty identical to the קרבן פסח,
Korban Pesach, sheep, one year, roasted, eaten day and a night, well
maybe that you can start eating during the day, really hard to
distinguish it from the קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, and it's a strict
obligation and so that's one issue. Then the חכמים Chachamim disagree and
they say it follows normal rules of a חגיגה Chagigah of a
שלמים. Shlamim. It is still unique in that normally a חגיגה Chagigah
is only brought when יום טוב Yom Tov begins and this is
brought on the 14th together with the קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, but
according to the חכמים Chachamim it and then there's another issue which
is, is it a strict obligation or is it optional? And you
could disagree with בן תימא Ben Tema and say that it has
its independent identity, it's cattle, two years and whatnot, but still believe
that it's a strict obligation. And what's the strict obligation? Well anything
that's a strict obligation on a particular time is brought even בשבת
be-Shabbat and even בטומאה. be-tumah. The גמרא Gemara uses the phrase קרבן
ציבור, Korban Tzibur, but as I told you the other day, קרבן
ציבור Korban Tzibur is really not even the relevant criterion. The relevant
criterion is that it's a קרבן שקבוע לו זמן. Korban she-kavua lo
zman. So it is possible that it could be brought even בשבת
be-Shabbat if you say that it's a real חיוב. chiyuv. But the
חכמים Chachamim disagree on that point as well, or there's another debate
about that about a certain person, what was his name, was פריש,
perish, יהודה בן דורתאי Yehuda ben Dortai that was פריש perish and
he separated himself off from the חכמים Chachamim and welcome Sally, long
time no see, great to have you.
And and and there was that was debated as well and that
became seemed to be very like heated issue about whether it could
be brought בשבת be-Shabbat or brought בטומאה. be-tumah. So it's two questions.
Is it an obligation, strict obligation or is it only brought in
order to be filled up so you eat the קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach when you are full or almost full? And then the other
question is how identical is it to the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach
itself? Okay, now within that discussion we also mentioned the idea that
the קרבן חגיגה Korban Chagigah that is brought on the חג chag
is brought
cannot be brought בשבת be-Shabbat on the חג, chag, but that's for
an obvious reason because that, although the ideal day is the first
day of יום טוב, Yom Tov, that could be brought as a
makeup on any other day, so therefore it would not override שבת.
Shabbat. So now actually is a moment to take a break and
to review what are the normal קרבנות korbanot that according to חז״ל
Chazal need to be brought on every
יום טוב. Yom Tov. Thank you very much. So on פסח Pesach
of course you bring a פסח Pesach on the 14th, that's before
יום טוב, Yom Tov, which we should actually just re-mention that פסח
Pesach is not the name of יום טוב. Yom Tov. The name
of יום טוב Yom Tov is חג המצות. Chag HaMatzot. פסח Pesach
is about the day of the קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, is about
the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach
and as we've been discussing together with that would come a special
קרבן חגיגה Korban Chagigah called חגיגת ארבעה עשר, Chagigat Arba'asar, חגיגה Chagigah
brought even before the חג, chag, and as I just said it's
somewhat of a debate, is that just to be full or is
that a strict obligation? To the degree that חגיגה Chagigah emphasizes the
idea that it's a חג, chag, it's an interesting to think that
if it's an obligation maybe that reflects the idea of the 14th
being a type of a חג, chag, which we've seen about a
discussion of not doing מלאכה, melachah, etc.
And isn't there זכר zecher to that, right, the חגיגת ארבעה עשר?
Chagigat Arba'asar?
Yeah, right, that's true. The like the זרוע zroa and the ביצה,
beitzah, the ביצה beitzah that we have on the סדר Seder plate
also is to remember the חגיגה. Chagigah. We obviously don't פוסק pasken
like בן תימא Ben Tema because we do something different than the
זרוע zroa to make it distinct. One minute. Now the other things
that you would bring on a normal יום טוב, Yom Tov, including
פסח Pesach but not limited to פסח Pesach are three. Number one,
there's the מצוה mitzvah of עולת ראיה, Olat Re'iyah, which we actually
which is you know יראה כל זכורך, yera'eh kol zchurecha,
all of your males, but then it says, fine, you show up,
you יראה, yera'eh, but at the end of that is ולא יראו
פני ריקם, ve-lo yer'u panai reikam, don't come empty-handed.
So from there we understand that there's a מצוה mitzvah to bring
a עולת ראיה, Olat Re'iyah, to bring a עולה olah when you
are coming to appear in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash for males
on the יום טוב. Yom Tov. Presumably if you don't appear in
the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash then you're just מבטל העשה, mevatel ha-aseh,
you're not doing העשה ha-aseh of bringing the ראיה, re'iyah, but if
you actually show up without a קרבן korban in hand then you
transgress the לא תעשה lo ta'aseh of ולא יראו פני ריקם. ve-lo
yer'u panai reikam. So if you're already showing up you better not
show up empty-handed. But there there is besides the לא תעשה lo
ta'aseh an עשה aseh to bring the
a עולה olah that's the עולת ראיה. Olat Re'iyah. This is discussed
in the first משנה mishnah of מסכת חגיגה, Masechet Chagigah, although this
is the עולה, olah, this is not the עולת ראיה, Olat Re'iyah,
not the חגיגה. chagigah. The second קרבן korban that we've been discussing
is the חגיגה, chagigah, when the תורה Torah says, right, or
when it says חג להשם, chag la-Shem, חג הסוכות. Chag HaSukkot. The
word's use of the word חג, chag, חז״ל Chazal understand that תחגו,
tachogu, so fascinatingly, what does that say? Celebrate. But חז״ל Chazal understand
in that word חג chag means that you recognize it as a
חג chag through the bringing of a קרבן חגיגה korban chagigah which
is a שלמים, shlamim, the owners eat the meat in ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
it's eaten for two days and the intervening night and it's a
קרבן korban that is brought on the חג, chag, on יום טוב.
Yom Tov. Again like the עולה, olah, ideally, or the ideally is
the wrong word, the primary obligation is the first day of יום
טוב. Yom Tov. If you did not bring it on the first
day of יום טוב, Yom Tov, you have makeup for the rest
of the חג. chag. On okay and on סוכות Sukkot you can
even make it up on שמיני עצרת. Shmini Atzeret. And on שבועות
Shavuot although it's only a one day חג, chag, we equate the
חגים chagim and not in this גמרא gemara elsewhere we say you
actually have six days to make it up on שבועות Shavuot just
as if it were פסח. Pesach. So that is the obligation of
demarcating it as a חג chag if you would ideally supposed to
be the first day. Again think about how many קרבנות korbanot people
are bringing. If it's פסח, Pesach, two קרבנות korbanot on ערב פסח,
Erev Pesach, right? Then the next day יום טוב Yom Tov two
more קרבנות, korbanot, right? ערב פסח Erev Pesach is the פסח Pesach
and חגיגת ארבעה עשר. chagigat arba'ah asar. On the fifteenth is the
עולת ראיה olat ri'ah and the חגיגת חג המצות. chagigat chag ha-matzot.
And then it says ושמחת לפני ה׳ אלקיך, ve-samachta lifnei Hashem Elokecha,
מצות שמחה mitzvot simcha which חז״ל Chazal also understand means שמחה simcha
through the bringing of קרבנות. korbanot. Why they didn't conflate it with
the חגיגה chagigah I don't know, they understand that there's a separate
obligation of bringing שלמי שמחה, shlamei simcha, a קרבן korban of שלמים
shlamim on the חג chag that is for the sake of שמחה
simcha and you eat it. And when we say אין שמחה אלא
בבשר ein simcha ella be-vasar
nowadays that we eat meat on יום טוב Yom Tov as a
way of שמחה, simcha, for חז״ל Chazal the original statement was אין
שמחה אלא בבשר שלמים, ein simcha ella be-vasar shlamim, that you bring
these שלמים shlamim and you eat them in the context of the
מקדש Mikdash and ירושלים Yerushalayim and that eating of it through connecting
with God that is the true שמחה, simcha, that's yet a third
קרבן. korban. Okay so we have a lot of קרבנות. korbanot. Let's
take a look now at
let's say you're a small family and you don't need that much.
Yeah exactly, exactly. That's not right, the חגיגה chagigah are brought just
to fill you up, these are separate obligations.
So as a group and it's just like פסח, Pesach, you bring
it not as an individual but a group.
Right, other קרבנות, korbanot, could you bring the other קרבנות korbanot as
a group as opposed to a קרבן יחיד? korban yachid?
It's an interesting question, it's an interesting question.
Like if you wanted to group up and save everybody some money,
right?
It would still have to be under the גדר geder of יחיד,
yachid, it's not a קרבן ציבור. korban tzibbur.
Right right right, only
two categories, so the question is could it be considered a קרבן.
korban.
Right right right right. In general the whole issue of a קרבן
שותפין korban shutafin is a somewhat of a questionable category about when
that applies. Now let me try to see what I can find
about that. Okay let's take a look now at the גמרא, gemara,
that's some background for what we're about to see.
So four lines from the bottom.
אמר עולא אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Ulla amar Rabbi Elazar, so עולא
Ulla says in the name of רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, the אמורא,
Amora, שלמים ששחטן מערב יום טוב, shlamim she-shachtan me-erev Yom Tov,
if you שחט shacht a שלמים shlamim ערב יום טוב, erev Yom
Tov, אינו יוצא בהן לא משום שמחה ולא משום חגיגה eino yotzei
bahen lo mishum simcha ve-lo mishum chagigah
and then you eat it at night, okay? Again whether it's ערב
פסח, erev Pesach, whether it's ערב סוכות, erev Sukkot, ערב שבועות, erev
Shavuot, we're not yet we're not specifically talking about פסח. Pesach. You
brought the קרבן korban the day ערב erev and you ate it
at night and maybe even ate it the next day because you
can eat it for two days and the middle night. You do
not fulfill your obligation of שמחה simcha even though you're eating on
the fifteenth, you're eating the meat of a שלמים, shlamim, but you
didn't שחט shacht on the fifteenth so it doesn't count for שמחה
simcha and it doesn't count for the חגיגה chagigah of the fifteenth
either. Let's see why not. משום שמחה דכתיב, Mishum simcha de-chtiv, you
don't fulfill your obligation of שמחה simcha because it
says וזבחת ושמחת, ve-zavachta ve-samachta, says you shall slaughter there and you
shall rejoice. Now that's actually not talking about שמחת יום טוב, simchat
Yom Tov, actually no it's talking about the קרבנות korbanot they would
bring on הר עיבל, Har Eival, so really it has nothing to
do with יום טוב, Yom Tov, but nevertheless the חז״ל Chazal understand
from there you learn a relationship. בעינן זביחה בשעת שמחה וליכא. Be'inan
zvicha be-sha'at simcha ve-leka. The זביחה zvicha has to be connected to
the joy, so it's actually not just the eating of the meat
of the קרבן, korban, it's the bringing of the קרבן korban that
creates a sense of joy and here's important, it's not just pleasure
it's joy and joy understood in this connection with God also evokes
the debate earlier about whether יום טוב Yom Tov is כולו לה׳
כולו לכם kulo la-Hashem kulo lachem and the bringing together of the
two through bringing and eating a קרבן. korban. So the joy has
to be through the bringing of the קרבן korban as well therefore
it has to be on יום טוב Yom Tov the bringing of
it to fulfill your obligation of שלמי שמחה shlamei simcha וליכא, ve-leka,
you don't have it. Now we will see a little later that
there is a dissenting opinion that says no as long as you
eat the meat on יום טוב Yom Tov you could have brought
it ערב יום טוב erev Yom Tov and actually according to the
רמב״ם Rambam we rule like that other opinion that it's all about
when you eat the meat. But this opinion says you have to
bring the קרבן korban on יום טוב. Yom Tov. משום חגיגה, Mishum
chagigah, now you don't fulfill your obligation of a חגיגה chagigah for
even a more basic reason. הוי דבר שבחובה, Havei davar she-be-chovah, since
it was a שלמים shlamim it was not a— specifically designated for
a חגיגה, Chaggigah, so it's like something that's a pre-existing obligation, meaning
it's not something if you made a נדר Neder a vow and
you sanctified this animal, you just had a קרבן, Korban, you have—that's
not good, you have to bring your חגיגה Chaggigah for something specifically
designated and not coming from any other obligation, it has to be
specifically for the purpose of the חגיגה. Chaggigah. וכל דבר שבחובה אינו
בא אלא מן החולין V'chol davar shebechova eino ba ela min hachulin
because the חגיגה Chaggigah is an obligatory thing, and anything that is
obligatory, I think I misread the first part. Anyway, חגיגה, Chaggigah, not
the קרבן, Korban, not the שלמים, Shlamim, the חגיגה Chaggigah is a
דבר שבחובה, davar shebechova, the חגיגה Chaggigah is obligatory, and anything that's
an obligatory, you have to come fresh, you can't bring from something
that's "Oh, it's a קרבן, Korban, I'll do double duty. I made
this as a שלמים, Shlamim, I made it as a נדר, Neder,
let's have it also count for my
חגיגה." Chaggigah. No.
Your חגיגה Chaggigah is an obligation, and therefore you can only bring
it from something that is not sanctified already and not already obligated
for another reason. Now I want to say two things. First of
all, I just got through telling you that a שלמים Shlamim was
an obligation, so a שלמי שמחה. Shalmei Simcha. So why not say
the same thing about שלמי שמחה, Shalmei Simcha, right? It was something
you had already sanctified, you can't use it. So רש"י Rashi quotes
a מדרשי הלכה midreshei halacha that say that there's an exception by
שלמי שמחה. Shalmei Simcha. שלמי שמחה Shalmei Simcha is the one thing
that although it's an obligation, you can double up.
And something that was already sanctified for another reason as a שלמים,
Shlamim, you had a שלמים Shlamim that you were supposed to give
a year ago because of a נדר Neder you took and you
finally got around to sanctifying it and it's because of this נדר
Neder and you sanctified it a week before סוכות, Succot, you can
nevertheless bring it on סוכות Succot and have it do double duty
as שלמי שמחה. Shalmei Simcha. That's the one exception to the rule.
You read רש"י, Rashi, he quotes you the מדרשי הלכה. midreshei halacha.
Okay, that's the one exception. Now, by the way, that makes sense
if we de-emphasized for the שלמי שמחה Shalmei Simcha the הקרבה. hakrava.
If you emphasize the eating of the meat, not the bringing of
the קרבן, Korban, then we understand, right? The problem is you can't
do something that has the double duty as a קרבן, Korban, but
the idea of שלמים Shlamim is eating the meat of a קרבן,
Korban, the eating, well, that's not the focus of my bringing the
קרבן, Korban, right? I could be bringing this for a נדר Neder
that I made a year ago, right? Hopefully not a year ago,
then it would have been over בל תאחר, bal te'acher, but I
made it a few months ago, right? And that's its one role.
Then I eat the meat as a שלמים, Shlamim, that's the שלמי
שמחה, Shalmei Simcha, that's the other role. It's not so much doing
double duty. So that's number one, first point. That שלמי שמחה Shalmei
Simcha you can—is the one type of obligatory קרבן Korban that you
can use another קרבן Korban to do, you can do double duty
to serve שלמי שמחה. Shalmei Simcha. The other issue that comes up
in this גמרא Gemara is that תוספות Tosafot says "I don't get
it," says תוספות. Tosafot. Even if you had brought this שלמים Shlamim
that you slaughtered on the fourteenth, even if you had brought it
on the fifteenth, it couldn't count for your חגיגה Chaggigah because of
the point I just told you of double duty. So why does
the גמרא Gemara say that you brought it on the fourteenth? Is
that clear? Meaning the גמרא Gemara says you can't use this קרבן
Korban you brought on the fourteenth to do double duty on the
fifteenth because a חגיגה Chaggigah has to be from fresh, can't be
something that's already been sanctified. So תוספות Tosafot basically says that if
that's true, and therefore even if you would wait a day, even
had you brought it on the fifteenth, it wouldn't count. Okay, so
he just wants to make that clear. So again, to repeat the
point that's being said: a שלמים, Shlamim, שלמי שמחה Shalmei Simcha is
an obligation, is an exception to a rule that even as an
obligation you can use a קרבן Korban to do double duty. But
the problem here is not that the קרבן Korban was already sanctified,
but that it was brought the day before. And according to this
opinion, for the שלמי שמחה Shalmei Simcha you have to bring it
on יום טוב, Yom Tov, you can't bring it before יום טוב,
Yom Tov, even if you're going to eat it on יום טוב.
Yom Tov. For the חגיגה, Chaggigah, that even had it been brought
on the fifteenth, because it was already sanctified, would not be good.
The חגיגה Chaggigah follows the general rule that it's an obligatory קרבן
Korban and you cannot use another קרבן, Korban, something sanctified for another
purpose, to do double duty to serve as your חגיגה. Chaggigah. Okay,
so those are the two points. Yes.
But according to that, though, if I designated it for another purpose,
I decide I'm
going
to bring it early for the sake of a חגיגה, Chaggigah, at
least I get out of that second part, right?
No, because if you—because it wouldn't be a sanctity of a חגיגה.
Chaggigah. If you sanctified it for a חגיגה Chaggigah בארבעה עשר, b'arba'ah
asar, there's no such thing as a חגיגה Chaggigah בארבעה עשר b'arba'ah
asar or פסח Pesach where there is, it's not the sanctity of
the קרבן. Korban. But תוספות Tosafot actually discusses something similar to your
scenario, so you can look at—I don't want to go there, you
can look at תוספות Tosafot לשלמים l'Shlamim on ע"א ע"ב. ayin aleph
amud bet. Let's take a look. So now the גמרא Gemara brackets
the idea of חגיגה Chaggigah and double duty and focuses on this
question of שלמים. Shlamim. Is it about when you brought the קרבן
Korban or when you ate the קרבן? Korban? Let's take a look.
לימא מסייע ליה. Leima mesayei lei. Let me try to bring a
proof to you. והיית אך שמח. V'hayita ach same'ach.
It says by סוכות, Succot, it says you shall—it says you shall
rejoice seven days. חג הסוכות—and Chag HaSuccot remember חג הסוכות Chag HaSuccot
means חגיגה—שבעת ימים. And then it says ושמחת בחגך, v'samachta bechagecha, again
חגיגה, Chaggigah שבעת ימים תחוג. shivat yamim tachog. By seven days תחוג,
tachog, again חגיגה. Chaggigah, Seven, seven, seven for the חגיגה. Chaggigah. And
then it ends by saying והיית אך שמח. v'hayita ach same'ach. והיית
אך שמח. vehayita ach same'ach. So what’s that telling you? לרבות לילו
יום טוב האחרון לשמחה, lerabot leilo Yom Tov ha'acharon lesimcha, that even
the last day of יום טוב, Yom Tov, the night of שמיני
עצרת, Shmini Atzeret, you can still bring... you can still eat your
meat of your חגיגה Chaggigah. and fulfill your obligation of חגיגה. chagiga
Now you didn’t bring it at night, you brought it the day
before, but you can eat it the night of שמיני עצרת Shmini
Atzeret and fulfill your obligation. אתה אומר ata omer לילו יום טוב
האחרון?
leilo Yom Tov
ha'acharon? What? I’ll talk about that. אתה אומר ata omer לילו יום
טוב האחרון? leilo Yom Tov ha'acharon? You’re telling me that I can
eat the meat the night of שמיני עצרת? Shmini Atzeret? או אינו
אלא לילו יום טוב הראשון? o eino ela leilo Yom Tov harishon?
Maybe I should be able to bring the קרבן korban on the
fourteenth and eat it the night of the first night of סוכות?
Sukkot? I’m just doing סוכות Sukkot so we don’t get confused with
the other things about פסח. Pesach. Anyway, and that’s the case of
the פסוק. pasuk. Maybe I should be able to eat it the
first night of סוכות Sukkot and also fulfill my obligation having brought
it on the fourteenth? תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, the verse teaches אך.
ach. However, אך ach is only. חלק chelek or חילק, chilek, it
divides. It’s not... it adds, the extra שמח same'ach adds an extra
שמחה, simcha, but אך ach says limited. So one of those nights,
not both of them. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? What’s the reason that
we chose to say if we had to include one night, we’re
going to include the last night, the night of שמיני עצרת, Shmini
Atzeret, and not the first night, the night of the first night
of סוכות? Sukkot? לאו משום דאין לו במה ישמח? lav mishum de'ein
lo bema yismach? It must be because the first night of סוכות
Sukkot you can’t do שמחה. simcha. You don’t have anything to do
שמחה simcha with. That שמחה simcha has to be with a קרבן
korban brought on יום טוב. Yom Tov. סבירא ליה, savira lei, that’s
why it’s not an option the first night, it’s only an option
the last night because the last night was a קרבן korban that
was brought during the יום טוב, Yom Tov, I mean יום טוב
Yom Tov including חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. So you see that proves
your idea that you need the קרבן korban to be brought on
יום טוב. Yom Tov. לא, lo, no, not necessarily. Maybe I could
say that you don’t need it brought on יום טוב, Yom Tov,
and nevertheless, we’re going to focus on the last night, not the
first. Why? כדתני טעמא, kidetani ta'ama, because the ברייתא braita itself gives
the end of the reason. מה ראית לרבות לילו יום טוב האחרון
ולהוציא לילו יום טוב הראשון? ma ra'ita lerabot leilo Yom Tov ha'acharon
ulehotzi leilo Yom Tov harishon? What motivates you to include the last
night and to exclude the first? מרבה אני לילו יום טוב האחרון,
marbe ani leilo Yom Tov ha'acharon, I include the last night שיש
שמחה לפניו, sheyesh simcha lefanav, because there’s a period of שמחה simcha
that precedes it. ומוציא אני לילו יום טוב הראשון, umotzi ani leilo
Yom Tov harishon, and I’m not going to include the first night
שאין שמחה לפניו, she'ein simcha lefanav, because the time that preceded it
wasn’t a time of שמחה. simcha. Which means, technically, you might... you
could שחט shacht it not during the
חג. chag. Okay, but then when would you eat it to be
יוצא? yotze? You eat it on the fifteenth in the day, okay,
because the מצוה... mitzvah... like that you would do. Okay, so there’s
no absolute exclusion of having been שחט shacht not on the חג.
chag. But if we have to choose between we’re going to include
one night and we have to choose between the night of the
fifteenth or the night of שמיני עצרת, Shmini Atzeret, we will say
let’s choose the night of שמיני עצרת Shmini Atzeret where we had
a period of שמחה simcha preceding it, rather than the night of
the fifteenth which did not. But that does not mean that it’s
not possible to שחט shacht it before and fulfill your obligation. You
just eat it on the day of the fifteenth, not the night
of the fifteenth. Okay? So that’s the answer. Now, of course, for
me I would say, first of all, if I had to choose
between the night of the fifteenth and the night of שמיני עצרת,
Shmini Atzeret, I would totally have chosen the night of the fifteenth.
It’s the first night of the חג, chag, so you’d think you’d
want to define the חג chag on the basis of it. And
שמיני עצרת Shmini Atzeret is anyway a חג בפני עצמו. chag bifnei
atzmo. But I think it’s important to note that probably... the question
is, I would even say otherwise. Why do you need a פסוק
pasuk to include the first night? If there’s a מצוה mitzvah to
תחוג tachog seven days, seven days includes the first night, doesn’t it?
So here I think what you have to understand is חז"ל’s Chazal
maybe hyper-reading sometimes of the word יום yom as literally daytime. So
therefore, if they start by the assumption that שבעת ימים shivat yamim.
means seven days and not nights, then we have to take a
second step to include nights. And if once you start with the
idea you have the days and then you say which night should
you include, so you’re going to be more likely to include the
night that follows the day because the day is where you start
from, rather than the night that precedes the day. That seems to
be what is going on here. Otherwise, it really doesn’t make any
sense. Okay, so that is the idea. So strictly speaking, you could
bring it ערב יום טוב, erev Yom Tov, as long as you
eat it the seventh... the first day.
But in the question of which night to include, we’re going to
include the night of שמיני עצרת, Shmini Atzeret, not the night of
the first night of יום טוב. Yom Tov. One more point is
that תוספות Tosafot says... רש"י Rashi says we’re only including the night.
And there’s a logic to that. Number one, by קרבנות, korbanot, although
by every other Jewish day the night precedes, by קרבנות korbanot the
day is the thing that comes first. You eat a קרבן korban
the day and the following night. Sometimes the day, the night, and
the day, but the basic unit is the day and the following
night. And given what I just told you, if you start with
the idea of seven days, so then we go include the nights,
so each day’s night is included, so the night of the fifteenth
is not included, every following night is included, and that gets you
the night of שמיני עצרת, Shmini Atzeret, but not the daytime. That’s
what רש"י Rashi says. תוספות Tosafot based on other considerations disagrees, and
he says once the night of שמיני עצרת Shmini Atzeret *Shemini Atzeret*
is included, the day of שמיני עצרת Shemini Atzeret *Shemini Atzeret* is
included as well, which by the way you could also hear since
the idea of the שלמים shlamim *Shelamim* is two days and a
night, if you're bringing it on the seventh, and then you're saying
it includes the night of the seventh, well, then it should also
include the day that follows, the night of the eighth, but it
should include the day that follows because a קרבן korban, *Korban* is
a day and night and a day. I don't know if I
just confused everybody. I'm glad I answered Michael's question.
So why,
I don't understand why the תלמוד *Talmud* says למימרא Lemaymra, מסייע ליה
*Lemeima Misayeia Leh*, there was no problem.
No, there was a claim, which we're going to see is
an opposing opinion to it in a little bit. The claim is
that you have to שחט shachted *Shecht* on יום טוב Yom Tov
*Yom Tov* as well. You can't שחט shachted *Shecht* ערב יום טוב
Erev Yom Tov? *Erev Yom Tov*. That's a new claim. Let's see
if we can find a supporting source. There's no challenge to it,
but let's just try to find a support. Okay, and we will
see in a minute that why, that there's actually are opposing opinions.
Okay? So it's just a מסייע *Mesayeia* to a new claim that
we haven't heard before, and let's see
if we can find a basis for it. Okay, so that's the
issue. A claim that you have to שחט shecht *Shecht* over the
חג chag *Chag*, can't be שחט shechted *Shecht* before, all about the
eating of the meat, although maybe that's an important part of it.
And this issue about the night of the first night as opposed
to the last night, and is there this sort of emphasis on
the day starting with the idea of bringing it on the day.
See, I thought that claim was justified by the פסוק pasuk, *Pasuk*
of וזבחת ושמחת *Vezavachta Vesamachta*. That was his own דרשה drasha *Drasha*.
That's just an אמורא *Amora* doing his own דרשה *Drasha*.
Okay, so we need something,
so they're not satisfied with, they're not satisfied with his own דרשה
*Drasha*. Right, yeah, they're not satisfied, it's your own דרשה *Drasha*, we
haven't heard this before, let's see if we can support it.
Is that in other words an אמורא *Amora* makes a דרשה *Drasha*,
the תלמוד *Talmud* would often then seek a more authoritative source? I
don't know.
I can't say if it's always when they make a דרשה *Drasha*,
but you do
have
למימרא Lemaymra, מסייע ליה *Lemeima Misayeia Leh* when a claim is made
that the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* thinks is not so clear. Right, okay,
when you listen to the רב *Rabbi* speak in שול *Shul*, aren't
you always thinking is that right? Where'd he get that from? That's
a nice little claim, but I don't know if I really believe
it. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: מתיב רב
יוסף *Moteeiv Rav Yosef*. Now רב יוסף *Rav Yosef* is going to
challenge this claim that you need to bring the שלמים shlamim *Shelamim*
on יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov* and you can't have brought
it from before יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov*. חגיגה chagiga. בארבעה
עשר יוצא yotzei בה משום שמחה simcha? ואין יוצא yotzei. בה משום
חגיגה chagiga *Chagiga be-asarya yotze bo mishum simcha ve-ein yotze bo mishum
chagiga*. So when we had yesterday the position of בן תימא *Ben
Tema*, who said that the חגיגה chagiga *Chagiga* of the 14th is
just like the קרבן korban פסח Pesach, *Korban Pesach* in so many
ways, he did say that, however, when you bring this חגיגה chagiga.
*Chagiga* on the 14th, the way the simple thing of what he
said is how רב יוסף *Rav Yosef* understands it, which is you
bring this חגיגה chagiga *Chagiga* on the 14th and then you're going
to eat it that night, and you fulfill your obligation of שמחה
simcha *Simcha* but you don't fulfill your obligation of חגיגה chagiga *Chagiga*,
the חגיגה chagiga *Chagiga* of the יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov*.
So that seems to be you שחט shecht *Shechted* it on the
14th with the קרבן korban. פסח Pesach *Korban Pesach*, you ate it
that night, the night of the 15th, and you get and it
accounts for שמחה simcha. *Simcha*, sounds like a pretty much of a
contradiction. אמאי *Amai*, why does it count for שמחה simcha *Simcha*? בעינן
זביחה בשעת שמחה simcha *Beeinan Zevicha Beshaat Simcha*, you have to שחט
shechted *Shecht* it at the time of שמחה simcha *Simcha*, you have
to שחט *Shecht* on יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov* according to
you. And here this חגיגה chagiga, *Chagiga* you שחט *Shechted* on the
14th and it still says eat it that night, ליל הסדר *Leil
Haseder*, and fulfill your obligation. And here you don't have שחיטה *Shechita*
at the time of שמחה simcha *Simcha*. So אמר רב אידי בר
אבין *Amar Rav Idi Bar Abin*, שעכביה ושחטה *She-ikveih Veshachta*. That you
held it over. When he says you fulfill your obligation of שמחה
simcha *Simcha*, it's not if you שחט *Shechted* it on the 14th.
It means you didn't שחט *Shecht* it on the 14th, you שחט
*Shechted* it on the 15th. And then you can use it for
שמחה simcha? *Simcha*, which is funny because then it doesn't sound like
what he's talking about, but if that's what he's talking about, the
point is what we said before, that even though this was presanctified
and sanctified for a different purpose, sanctified for the חגיגה chagiga, *Chagiga*
of the 14th, if you held it over and שחט *Shechted* it
on the 15th, it can do double duty. The idea of שלמי
שמחה Shalmei Simcha. *Shalmei Simcha*, you can use another קרבן korban *Korban*
for שלמי שמחה Shalmei Simcha *Shalmei Simcha*. So that's how he reads
it. Not that it was brought on the 14th, but that it
was reused or repurposed on the 15th, it hadn't been brought on
the 14th and that's okay for the idea of שלמי שמחה shalmei
simcha, *Shalmei Simcha*. Double dipping. Double duty, I would say.
אמר רב אשי *Amar Rav Ashi*, הכי נמי מסתברא *Hachi Nami Mistabra*.
That also makes sense that we're talking about not that you שחט
*Shechted* it on the 15th, not the 14th, this thing that was
sanctified for the 14th. דאי לא Lo, תימא הכי *De-ee Lo Teima
Hachi*, הא מתניתא מאן תנא לה *Ha Matnita Man Tana Lah*? Who
is the author of that ברייתא braisa, *Baraita* that speaks about this
חגיגה chagiga *Chagiga* being used for שמחה simcha *Simcha*? בן תימא *Ben
Tema*. It was בן תימא *Ben Tema*, that was the whole ברייתא
braisa *Baraita* we quoted yesterday. בן תימא הפוסל בלינה *Ben Tema hapaseil
belina*. So when should you be, when would you be eating this
חגיגה Chagiga *Chagiga* to fulfill your obligation of שמחה simcha *Simcha*? I
said you ate it ליל הסדר *Leil Haseder*, but there's a problem
saying you ate it ליל הסדר *Leil Haseder*, right? Because what did
we just learn a few minutes ago? When does the מצווה *Mitzvah*
of שמחה simcha *Simcha* begin? When does the idea of eating a
קרבן korban *Korban* of שלמי שמחה shalmei simcha. *Shalmei Simcha* begin? The
day of the 15th, not the night. That was the whole point.
So if I שחט *Shechted* this on the 14th and I want
to use it for the מצווה *Mitzvah*... of שמחה simcha *simcha*, I
have to wait till I can't eat it ליל סדר *Leil Seder*.
I have to wait till the day of the fifteenth. Ah, but
according to בן תימא *Ben Teima*, he says that this is just
like the קרבן korban פסח Pesach *Korban Pesach* and and the clock
runs out at by daybreak. You only have the nighttime to eat
it. So we're really stuck, right? You can't be eating it at
night because שמחה simcha. *simcha* doesn't apply yet, of שמחה simcha. *simcha*
through קרבנות korbanot *korbanot* at least. And so by the day, it's
already פסול pasul *pasul*. So it cannot be talking that you שחט
*shechted* it on the
fourteenth. Okay, so שמע מינה *shema mina*. That's a pretty darn good
proof. Once you assume once you start with the assumption that you
cannot do שמחה simcha *simcha* the night before. Okay, מתיב רבא *mative
Rava*. Now רבא *Rava* is going to challenge it. So now you
see though why the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* wanted to prove it because
a lot of אמוראים *Amoraim* have problems with it. Right. Exactly. ההלל
והשמחה *Hahallel ve'hasimcha* this is a משנה *mishna* in סוכה sukkah *Sukkah*.
The מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* of הלל *Hallel* and שמחה simcha. *simcha* over
סוכות Sukkot *Sukkot* שמונה *shmoneh* is eight days. Okay, eight days of
הלל *Hallel* because of שמיני עצרת Shemini Atzeret *Shmini Atzeret* and also
שמחה simcha *simcha* the שלמי שמחה simcha *shalmei simcha* even goes through
presumably שמיני עצרת *Shmini Atzeret*. ואי אמרת ובעינן זביחה בשעת שמחה simcha
*Ve'im amarta ve'inan zvicha besha'at simcha*, and if you say however that
you can only have שחיטה *shechting* at the time of שמחה simcha
*simcha*, at the time of יום טוב Yom Tov, *yom tov*, הזימנין
סגיאין דלא משכחת לה אלא שבעה *hazmanim sagi'im dlo mashkachat lah ela
shiva*. You're most of the time or many not most many times
only going to have seven days of שלמי שמחה simcha *shalmei simcha*.
Why would you only have seven days of שלמי שמחה simcha *shalmei
simcha*? כגון שחל יום טוב Yom Tov, ראשון rishon. להיות בשבת *Kegon
shechal yom tov rishon lihyot beshabbat*. If the first day of סוכות
Sukkot *Sukkot* falls out on שבת Shabbos *Shabbat*. Meaning what? Meaning you
have to according to this משנה *mishna*, you have to or you're
able to I'll talk about that in a minute have שלמי שמחה
simcha *shalmei simcha* all eight days. There's an eight-day idea period of
שלמי שמחה simcha *shalmei simcha*. Now, when am I bringing the קרבן
korban *korban*? So if you say that I can bring it on
ערב יום טוב Erev Yom Tov *erev yom tov* and eat it
on יום טוב Yom Tov *yom tov*, fine. So I'll always have
a chance to eat on eight days. Why? Because every day will
either be a weekday or the day before will be a weekday.
So even if the day is a שבת *Shabbat*, I could always
bring it the day before and eat it the following day. Because
you don't bring שלמי שמחה simcha, *shalmei simcha* on שבת *Shabbat*. But
if you say so that then fine, I'll have eight days opportunity
to eat שלמי שמחה simcha. *shalmei simcha*. But if you say that
you cannot that you can't bring it on the fourteenth, then when
the fifteenth is when the fourteenth when the fifteenth is שבת *Shabbat*,
I can't bring it on the fifteenth, I can't bring it on
the fourteenth, there's going to be a day that I'm not going
to have שלמי שמחה simcha *shalmei simcha*.
You're right, many most times.
Alright, so that's the answer. But this is his question. So
the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says,
so
אמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהודה *amar Rav Huna brei de'Rav Yehuda*
משמח בשעירי הרגלים *misamcha besairei ha'regalim*. Ah, here's what you could do.
You can't eat the שלמים shlamim *shlamim* when the fifteenth is שבת
*Shabbat* because you couldn't have brought it on the fourteenth and you
can't bring it today, but what you can do is eat the
meat of the שעיר החטאת *seir hachatat*. Okay, because with every מוסף
*musaf* you'd bring עולה *olah*, there's no meat left to eat עולה
*olah*, but there's always a שעיר החטאת *seir hachatat*, a sin offering
of a goat. So you could eat that meat. Of course, what?
Who gets to eat that meat? And how many people are eating
the meat of the שעיר החטאת *seir hachatat*? So אמר רבא Amar
Rava, שתי קושיות בדבר *amar Rava shte kushuot badavar*. I got two
answers to that. חדא *Chada*, number one, דשעירי הרגלים חי נאכלין chai
ne'echalin, ולא מבושל *d'seirei ha'regalim chai ne'echalin v'lo mivushal*. First of all,
if you're bringing it on שבת *Shabbat*, these this חטאת chatas *chatas*,
okay, and you wanted to eat it on שבת *Shabbat*, guess what?
You have to eat it raw. Okay, because you're allowed to do
a מלאכה *melacha* to bring it as a קרבן korban *korban*, the
fixed קרבנות korbanot. *korbanot* you bring on שבת *Shabbat*, but you don't
do a מלאכה *melacha* in order to be able to eat it
that day. So you'd have to eat it raw. ושמחה בחי ליכא
*Ve'simcha bechai leka*.
And there is no joy in eating raw meat. Okay, I guess
you never
had steak Steak tartare? Steak tartare. Carpaccio. Tartare or something. Anyway, where
they chop it up anyway, okay, fine. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* didn't
buy the
גמרא *Gemara* didn't buy into those newfangled things. How do you read
that line? How do you read that line?
ושמחה בחי ליכא *Ve'simcha bechai leka*.
We have no joy in our lives. No. שמחה simcha, *simcha*
joy with raw meat does not exist. You don't get any joy
out of eating raw meat.
Alright, the words right before that.
Oh, חי *chai* those goat, the...
The שעירי רגלים חי נאכלין, צלי אי נאכלין. tzli ei ne'echalin. They
could be eaten, צלי אי נאכלין. tzli ei ne'echalin. Okay. ועוד, ve'od,
number one. Number two, כהנים אוכלין. kohanim ochlin. The only people that
eat that are כהנים, kohanim, ישראל לא מסמכאן. Yisrael lo masmchan.
So obviously how does everybody else have any שמחה? So that's not
an answer. So we still have our question. How do you have
eight days of שמחה when יום טוב Yom Tov, falls on שבת
if you can't bring it on ערב יום טוב? Erev Yom Tov,
אלא אמר רב פפא משמחו בכסות נקייה ויין ישן. Ella amar Rav
Papa misamcho biksut nekiya veyayin yashan.
All right, so you do like you do nowadays. You don't have
a meat of a קרבן, korban you buy some nice clothes, you
have some old wine. So you have like the alternative we have
nowadays when we don't have שלמי שמחה. Of course that's like a
real you know a real weak answer because obviously if we're fundamentally
talking about a חיוב קרבן chiyuv korban and then talking about some
weak substitute instead of throwing it all together. Anyway I just it's
very I do want to put out there two points. Number one
two points about this about the relationship of the קרבן korban and
the regular how we do שמחה.
First of all I'll say a few things. Some people
are מקפיד makpid to have meat on יום טוב Yom Tov. because
אין שמחה אלא בבשר ein simcha ela bebasar like on שבועות Shavuot
to make a point of having מילכיגס milchigs and then having after
the מילכיגס milchigs you take away the מילכיגס milchigs and then you
have your meat meal. As you see from this גמרא, first of
all this גמרא when it spoke about the absence of קרבנות korbanot.
didn't even mention meat. It just said יין yayin you know nice
wine and good clothes. And even other גמרות Gemaros you know you
know say בשר ויין basar veyayin I mean there's a lot of
alternatives. There's no strict need of meat according if you really look
close at the sources you know okay it could be debated but
the simple sense is there's no strict need of meat when you're
not having the meat of a שלמים shlamim the meat of a
קרבן. korban Number one. But number two also when we do it
nowadays שמחה you know I nobody we just got through saying שמחה
doesn't start on the first night of the חג chag really? So
like if I came to your סוכה Sukkah on the first night
of the חג chag. I would say you know you don't have
to make such a nice meal because שמחה doesn't begin until tomorrow.
Right? It's absurd. Right? The מצוה mitzvah of שמחה starts at the
beginning of the חג. chag So only in the קרבן korban context
with this emphasis of starting in the day and all these various
things that we spoke about you know that's where it starts you
know the day of the 15th. But when it becomes the non-קרבן
korban context of שמחה obviously it has different parameters. And one final
thing I want to say which is how extensive is this obligation
of שמחה? Like you know especially if you think about the רמב"ם
Rambam for example says you know when he speaks about the מצוה
mitzvah of שמחה he mentions you know not only the קרבן korban
but the generalized idea of rejoicing he ties it into שמחת בית
השואבה Simchat Beit HaShoeva on סוכות Sukkot you know סוכות Sukkot? is
the חג chag. where the תורה Torah most emphasizes שמחה אך שמח
ach samayach so we assume that the מצוה mitzvah is throughout the
חג. chag
So am I חייב chayiv to bring a קרבן korban, every single
day right? If I have a מצוה mitzvah of שמחה throughout the
חג chag or maybe every other day because I can eat it
for two days so am I really חייב chayiv to bring a
קרבן korban every every day or every other day? So the תוספות
Tosafot a little bit sounds like yes but the רמב"ם Rambam sounds
like no. He says the מצוה mitzvah of שמחה in the context
of a קרבן korban, means at least one more קרבן korban over
the חג chag, for the purpose of שמחה. Okay it doesn't mean
that you have to do it every day. It means one extra
thing one extra קרבן korban for the purpose of שמחה. So when
we say for example that שמחה is the last night according to
the רמב"ם Rambam it doesn't mean you have an obligation to have
you know do a קרבן korban so you can eat the last
night it means if you haven't had a chance until now even
the last night can be when you do your מצוה mitzvah of
שמחה. Okay but it is interesting the difference of שמחה as experienced
through the קרבן korban, of שלמי שמחה as opposed to the שמחה
as we do it when we don't have קרבנות. Okay yeah
somebody we haven't heard from yet. Yes today today.
Is this the where do you get the extensive idea that every
סוכות מצוה mitzvah has to be or has might have to have
meat like at least at a ברית bris which has meat? Right
right.
Could be I mean because the point is when you if you
say אין שמחה אלא בבשר ein simcha ela bebasar and you understand
that there's an idea of שמחה maybe not just שמחת יום טוב
simchas yom tov of course you know right and we do have
the idea you know that I mean the whole concept of שמחה
is why during such things you know why when things happen you
don't say תחנון tachanun and so on. So even though it's not
a day of שמחה like a יום טוב if it's an event
of שמחה yeah I assume that that is related yeah.
Which means that if the last day שמיני עצרת is a רגל
בפני עצמו regel bifnei atzmo would you do all these other things
again?
No not for that purpose. The whole purpose that it's a רגל
בפני עצמו regel bifnei atzmo is you don't have these חיוב chiyuv
of קרבנות. We'll worry about it when we get to סוכה when
we talk about רגל בפני עצמו. regel bifnei atzmo. Now the גמרא
says like this.
Okay so כי אתא רבין אמר רבי אלעזר ki ata Rabin amar
Rabbi Elazar now that was what עולא Ulla said in the name
of רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar now when רבין Rabin came from ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael he had a different version of what רבי אלעזר
Rabbi Elazar said. שלמים ששחטן מערב יום טוב יוצא בהן משום שמחה.
Shlamim sheshachatan me'erev yom tov yotzei ban mishum simcha. No it's the
exact opposite of what you heard in רבי אלעזר's Rabbi Elazar's name.
If you שחט on ערב יום טוב Erev Yom Tov, and you
eat the meat on יום טוב you fulfilled your obligation of שמחה
ואין יוצא בהן משום חגיגה ve'ein yotzei ban mishum chagiga that still
doesn't do חגיגה chagiga that has to be something that was שחט
on יום טוב that was specifically designated for חגיגה chagiga but for
שלמים shlamim but for שמחה you do. יוצא בהן משום שמחה. yotzei
ban mishum simcha. יוצא בו משום שמחה לא בעינן זביחה בשעת שמחה.
Yotzei bo mishum simcha lo ba'inan zvicha b'sha'as simcha. You don't have
to שחט it on יום טוב, and you could do double duty,
even though it was a שלמים shlamim for a different purpose, as
long as you're eating the meat on יום טוב, you fulfill your
obligation.
ולא משום חגיגה, V'lo mishum chagiga, but it doesn't count as a
חגיגה. chagiga הוי דבר שבחובה, Havei davar she'bechova, חגיגה chagiga is obligatory,
וכל דבר שבחובה אינו בא אלא מן החולין, v'chol davar she'bechova eino
ba ela min hachullin, חולין, chullin, and it has to come from
something that was not previously sanctified, and also תוספות Tosfos would say
it would have to be brought on the יום טוב itself. Now
that's really important because again it shows, you know, when we were
learning for the last few weeks about the פסח, Pesach I told
you the פסח Pesach is unique that it's the one קרבן korban,
that is brought not for the purpose of the זריקה, zerika, but
for the purpose of being able to eat the meat that night,
right? It's all brought for the purpose of אכילה. achila. Well, according
to this, שלמים shlamim, is somewhat similar because you could bring the
שלמים shlamim. on ערב יום טוב, you could have brought it from
another קרבן, korban some other thing that was sanctified for a different
purpose, and it doesn't matter as long as you're eating the meat
of some קרבן korban. on יום טוב, you fulfill your obligation of
שמחה, even if it was brought ערב יום טוב, even if it
was sanctified for a different purpose. Presumably you can't use your פסח
Pesach to count for שלמי שמחה, that I don't know exactly why,
well, maybe because the מצוה mitzvah only starts on the day, not
at the night, but as long as starting the day you're eating
some meat of some קרבן, korban you're יוצא שלמי שמחה. So that
also really emphasizes the eating and not the bringing.
Even if it's a חטאת chatas, though, right?
יש שלמי שמחה?
Yesh
shalmei simcha?
No, presumably if you're a כהן Kohen and you ate the meat
of a חטאת, why not? Okay, so if that's the
case, so why do you have to wait for the morning for
the מצוה mitzvah to start?
Yeah, so that's very bizarre, I understand, still then the emphasis on
the morning. Yeah, I don't have a good explanation. Okay, מיתיבי, Meisivei,
they asked on this. So now we're going to go through everything
we just did before so it'll go quickly. והיית אך שמח, V'hayisa
ach samei'ach, לרבות ליל יום טוב האחרון לשמחה. lerabbos leil Yom Tov
ha'acharon l'simcha. Everything that was a question was a what is now
a support and everything that was a support is a question. Okay,
והיית אך שמח, V'hayisa ach samei'ach, you should be, this is the
ברייתא, baraita happy, לרבות ליל יום טוב האחרון לשמחה. lerabbos leil Yom
Tov ha'acharon l'simcha. The last the night of שמיני עצרת is part
of שמחה. אתה אומר לרבות ליל יום טוב האחרון Atah omer lerabbos
leil Yom Tov ha'acharon you say it includes the night of שמיני
עצרת או אינו אלא לרבות ליל יום טוב הראשון o eino ela
lerabbos leil Yom Tov harishon maybe it should be the first night
of סוכות? תלמוד לומר אך חלק וחלק. Talmud lomar ach chilek v'chalak.
אך Ach
it split. לאו כל הלילות, Lav kol haleilos, it's not all nights.
מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, why what's the difference? לאו משום דאין לו
במה ישמח Lav mishum de'ein lo be'ma yismach isn't it because the
first night you can't do the מצוה of שמחה because you can't
you can't use meat from a קרבן that was brought the day
before? לא, no, that's not the reason. You could use meat from
a קרבן the day before and you could use it on the
day of the fifteenth. So why not the night of the fifteenth?
כדתניא, Kedisanya, like the ברייתא baraita says, מה ראית לרבות ליל יום
טוב האחרון ולהוציא ליל יום טוב הראשון, mah ra'isa lerabbos leil Yom
Tov ha'acharon u'lehotzi leil Yom Tov harishon, why are you including the
last night and excluding the first night? מרבה אני ליל יום טוב
האחרון, Marbeh ani leil Yom Tov ha'acharon, I include the last night
שיש שמחה לפניו she'yesh simcha lefanav because it's preceded by שמחה, ומוציא
אני ליל יום טוב הראשון, u'motzi ani leil Yom Tov harishon, I
exclude the first night שאין שמחה לפניו she'ein simcha lefanav that it's
not preceded. Again with this as I said, this emphasis on starting
with the basis of the idea of the daytime, then you include
the night after not the night before. But technically but yes if
you שחט it on the fourteenth and you ate it today of
the fifteenth you would be יוצא. אמר רב כהנא מניין לאימורי חגיגת
חמישה עשר שנפסלים בלינה. Amar Rav Kahana minayin l'imurei chagigas chamisha asar
she'nifsalim b'lina. By the way, the רמב"ם Rambam פוסק paskens like that
opinion that you can actually שחט the day before and still fulfill
your obligation. אמר רב כהנא מניין לאימורי חגיגת חמישה עשר שנפסלים בלינה,
Amar Rav Kahana minayin l'imurei chagigas chamisha asar she'nifsalim b'lina, how do
you know that the fats of the חגיגה chagiga, of the fifteenth,
right? You bring this חגיגה chagiga on the fifteenth. Now how long
can you eat the meat? Right, in a normal שלמים shlamim how
long do you eat the meat? Two days and the intervening night.
When do the fats that have to be burned on the מזבח,
mizbe'ach, how long can they be burned? Can they be burned as
long as the meat can be eaten?
No, they have to be burned the night following the הקרבה. hakrava.
So the the expiration date on the אימורין imurin is prior to
that of the meat. Right, the end of the הקרבה hakrava of
the קרבן has to end by the following night, which is the
burning of the fats, the eating of the meat can proceed another
day, at least another daytime. Okay, how do we know that? So
it's not just about the
חגיגה, chagiga it's really about any שלמים, shlamim that's what תוספות Tosfos
says, it's really about every שלמים. מניין לאימורי חגיגת חמישה עשר שנפסלים
בלינה, Minayin l'imurei chagigas chamisha asar she'nifsalim b'lina, how do you know
they become פסול pasul? by sleeping over just the following night before
the meat becomes becomes פסול?
pasul Does that mean that if the if the אימורין imurin become
פסול pasul because they have not been consumed by the הקרבה hakrava
that then I cannot eat the meat after that?
No, you can still eat the meat. There is some discussion, there
is some, well, there they are somewhat linked. There is some discussion
that we had before about, you know, about that the burning of
the אימורין imurin somehow, you know, after the אימורין imurin are burned
the בעלים be'alim are able to eat the meat. But but בדיעבד
b'diavad not. But at least in a לכתחילה lechatchila way they are
linked, but בדיעבד b'diavad not. שנאמר, She'ne'emar, the verse says, ולא ילין
חלב חגי עד בוקר. v'lo yalin chelev chagi ad boker. You cannot
let the fat of my חג, chag, right, which is now the
חגיגה, chagiga sleep over till the next morning. Now which morning? Maybe
it means the morning of... of the 16th? How do we know
it means the morning of—or I mean maybe it means the morning
of the 17th? 17th. Right. וסמיך ליה Usmech lei ראשית. Reshit. The
next pasuk is ראשית בכורי אדמתך. Reshit bikurei admatecha. So we read
it as בוקר ראשית, Boker reshit, the first morning. So you can't—so
you can't let it stay even until the immediate preceding morning. למימרא,
Lemaymra... so fine, that's the דרשא. derasha. And that's how we know
that that expiration is the following night even though the meat is
longer. למימרא, lemaymra, that suggests that האי בוקר בוקר ראשון. hai boker,
boker rishon. למימרא...
wait
a minute. Yeah. Right, right, right. So
למימרא, sorry, sorry, I'm predicting the next slot. So right, to tell
you the ראשית Reshit tells you that האי בוקר בוקר ראשון, hai
boker, boker rishon, it's the first morning. מתקיף לה רב יוסף, Maskif
lei Rav Yosef, so Rav Yosef asked on this: טעמא דכתיב ראשית,
Ta'ama dechetiv reshit, the way you know it means the first morning
it becomes invalid is because it says ראשית, Reshit, right, and you
get to read it the first morning. הא לא כתב ראשית, Ha
lo katav reshit, had it not written that, הוה אמינא מאי בוקר
בוקר שני. hava amina mai boker, boker sheni. You would have been
prepared to say that when it says don't let stay until the
morning it means two mornings from now, not the immediate morning. So
how could that have been a possibility? מי איכא מידי, Mi ika
midi, could there ever be a case דבשר איפסלי מאורתא debhasar ipsalei
me'orta that the meat would already have been invalid that night, ואימורין
עד צפרא, ve'imurin ad tzafra, and the fat not until the next
morning? Meaning, maybe I can just,
if I just illustrated it
here, here's the 15th, right?
You have day and then the following night, which halakhically is the
16th, and you have day and night. Okay, so you're bringing your
קרבן, your חגיגה chagiga here, right? You're eating it—I'll make it E—you're
eating it right up through the day, right? Now in terms of
the fats—that'll be F—okay, it says, "Don't let it stay until the
next morning." So there's two ways to read that. Don't let it
stay until morning number one, right? This is morning number one. This
is morning number two. Okay, this is morning number one, this is
morning number two. "Don't let it stay until morning number one," so
it becomes פסול pasul. here, before the meat becomes פסול. pasul Right,
that's how we פסקינן. pasken. Or he says, "That I learn because
it said ראשית." Reshit. So he said, "How could it have meant
anything else?" Even without the word ראשית, Reshit, what were you going
to say? You're going to say it means that it's morning number
two? So you would have the fat be more kosher than the
meat? The meat stops being able to be eaten at the night
and the fats get the whole next day? That's not a possibility.
The fats are part of the הקרבה hakrava of the קרבן, they
clearly have an earlier expiration date, not a later expiration date than
actually the meat itself.
You put them on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. It stays as long as
it stays.
All right, that's a question. But his question is that there's no
way that would have been given more time than the actual eating
of the meat.
Maybe I should have said M for meat, but F is for
fat. But he said that the fat is for the גבוה. Gavo'ah.
I would say that it can last longer.
Okay, so you and Michael agree. He doesn't like that. Let's see
what the Gemara says. So he says,
מי איכא מידי דבשר איפסלי מאורתא, mi ika midi debhasar ipsalei me'orta,
is there anything that the meat would become פסול pasul the night,
the night, you know, the night of the
16th, ואימורין עד צפרא, ve'imurin ad tzafra, and you could still burn
and you could still burn the fats all until the next morning
of the 17th? אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, so Abaye said,
אלמה לא, almah la, why not? See, you have Abaye behind you.
הרי פסח לרבי אלעזר בן עזריה, Harei Pesach le-Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah,
how about the פסח itself according to Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah? He
says you can only eat the פסח until midnight. Okay, and that's
why some people are מקפיד makpid to get to the אפיקומן afikoman
by midnight.
דבשר איפסלי מחצות, Debhasar ipsalei mechatzot, so the meat—the clock runs out
midnight—ואימורין עד צפרא, ve'imurin ad tzafra, and the fats you can burn
the whole until the next morning. So it's not a crazy thought
to think you would have had more time for the fats rather
than less time. אמר רבא, so Rava said, רב יוסף הכי קא
קשיא ליה. Rav Yosef hachi ka kashya lei. All right, here's what
was really bothering Rav Yosef. Rashi even says here, you know sometimes
the Gemara rereads something. Rashi even says here, "Although he didn't say
it, here's what was bothering him." Admit that we're not right, we
can't fit this into the words, but here's what was bothering him
was the possibility that בוקר boker could have meant even in a
הוה אמינא hava amina the second morning. Here's what was bothering him.
מי איכא מידי, Mi ika midi, is there ever a time דאילו
תנא לבשר לא בעי ראשית, de'ilu tanna lebhasar lo ba'ei reshit, רב
כהנא לאימורין בעי
ראשית? Rav Kahana le'imurin ba'ei reshit? I will show you that in
another ברייתא baraita? we don't need the word ראשית. Reshit. The word
בוקר boker automatically means the immediate next morning. So why does Rav
Kahana need the word ראשית? Reshit? בוקר boker we see in other
places means the next morning and there's no question that to think
that it might mean two mornings. It means the immediate next morning.
Where do we—and he says that even by—even by the meat, which
is more מיקל, meykel, a ברייתא baraita: we're going to see that
assumes בוקר boker means the immediate morning. So certainly by אימורין imurin
which are more strict, בוקר boker should immediately mean the next morning.
What is this ברייתא? Braita Let's take a look. מאי היא דתניא,
Mai hi? Detanya, taught in a ברייתא: Braita לא ילין מן הבשר
אשר תזבח בערב ביום הראשון לבוקר. lo yalin min habhasar asher tizbach
ba'erev bayom harishon laboker. Don't let the meat that you slaughter that
evening stay over until the next morning. ביום הראשון, Bayom harishon, on
the first... stay over till the next morning. That's very complicated. When
are you שוחט shochting it? Which בקר boker is it staying over
till? So let's take a look. So we understand this is talking
about the חגיגה chagiga of the 14th. Okay, and the way we
read it is don't let the meat stay over stay over you
have בערב ביום הראשון ba'erev ba'yom ha'rishon you get to eat it
two days like you get to eat a normal שלמים two days,
but don't let it stay over לבוקר la'boker the morning following the
15th, right? 'Cause he slaughtered it on the 14th, he eats it
the 14th, the 15th, and don't let it stay over. So let's
take a look. What? Don't let it stay over till the 16th.
Okay. Now, but it's hard it's a hard פסוק, pasuk. right? So
let's see what the גמרא what the ברייתא Braita. does with it.
לימד על חגיגת ארבעה עשר Limed al chagigat arba'ah asar this teaches
you that the חגיגה chagiga of the 14th שנאכלת לשני ימים ולילה
אחד she'ne'echelet lishnei yamim v'laila echad is eaten for two days and
the intervening night. Right, so let's see it it's going to unpack
itself. Okay. או אינו אלא יום ולילה, O eino ela yom valaila,
maybe not, maybe it means don't let it stay over ביום הראשון
עד בוקר ba'yom ha'rishon ad boker to the morning of the 15th.
Okay, which is a reasonable read of the פסוק. pasuk? כשהוא אומר
ביום הראשון, K'shehu omer ba'yom ha'rishon, no, it says ביום הראשון, ba'yom
ha'rishon, which we mean to mean that you can eat it on
יום הראשון. yom ha'rishon. הרי בוקר שני אמור, Harei boker sheni amur,
so so when it says לבוקר, la'boker, it can't it's already saying
that you eat it on יום הראשון, yom ha'rishon, so בוקר boker
means the בוקר boker following following the 15th.
That's בוקר boker of the 16th.
What? Well let's take a look cause it's not done. או אינו
אלא לבוקר ראשון, O eino ela l'voker rishon, so it like goes
back you know, which is funny. It thought it proved it and
then it repeats the question. No, maybe it means the morning of
the 15th. מני מקיים חגיגה נאכלת לשני ימים ולילה אחד, Ma'ni mekayem
chagiga ne'echelet lishnei yamim v'laila echad, so how about the idea that
we generally know that a חגיגה chagigah is eaten for two days
and the middle night? חוץ מזו, Chutz mizu, other חגיגות chagigot like
a חגיגה chagigah of of a normal חג, but the חגיגה chagigah
of the 14th maybe it means ביום הראשון עד בוקר, ba'yom ha'rishon
ad boker, the morning of the 15th it's invalid. כשהוא אומר בו,
K'shehu omer bo, when it says about a חגיגה אם נדר או
נדבה זבח קרבנו ביום זבחו
יאכל וממחרת והנותר ממנו chagiga im neder o nedava zevach korbano b'yom
zivcho ye'achel umimacharat v'hanotar mimenu what's the פסוק?
pasuk באש ישרף. Ba'esh yasaref. Right.
Anyway, so that the end of that פסוק pasuk is that you
have two days to eat to eat a normal like שלמים and
we learn from that פסוק pasuk somehow that that's including even a
חגיגה, chagigah Rabbi says it's somehow the extra word אם. im. לימד,
Limed, we have a tradition that that פסוק pasuk, teaches you חגיגת
ארבעה עשר שנאכלת לשני ימים ולילה אחד. chagigat arba'ah asar she'ne'echelet lishnei
yamim v'laila echad. That's crazy, right though, right? What how does it
think to read the פסוק, pasuk why does it ask the question
again, and at the end of the day where's it learning from
this פסוק נדר או נדבה pasuk neder o nedava to talk about
the חגיגה chagigah of the 14th? So we've gotta we're gonna now
try to unpack the whole ברייתא Braita. and then we're gonna get
back to saying how that what the problem here was with with
the דרשה about the אימורים. eimurim. Let's take a look. אמר מר,
Amar mar, now so let's figure out this ברייתא. או אינו אלא
בוקר ראשון, O eino ela boker rishon, maybe it means the first
morning is when it becomes invalid. האמרת כשהוא אומר ביום הראשון הרי
בוקר שני אמור, Ha'amarta k'shehu omer ba'yom ha'rishon harei boker sheni amur,
what are you talking about? Somehow you thought in the previous line
that the word ביום הראשון ba'yom ha'rishon meant you got to eat
it on the first day. So how did you turn around and
say oh well maybe it means you burn maybe it means it's
burnt on the first 15th day. הכי קאמר, Hachi ka'amar, here's how
to read this ברייתא. או אינו אלא בשתי חגיגות, O eino ela
bishtei chagigot, maybe the way you read this פסוק pasuk, it's talking
about two חגיגות. chagigot. הכתוב מדבר. Ha'katuv medaber. אחת חגיגת ארבעה עשר
ואחת חגיגת חמשה עשר, Achat chagigat arba'ah asar v'achat chagigat chamishah asar,
the חגיגה chagigah. of the 14th and the חגיגה chagigah of the
15th. וזו לבוקרה וזו לבוקרה, V'zu l'vokrah v'zu l'vokrah,
and each one has its morning. So meaning here's how we would
read the פסוק, pasuk okay. It says ולא ילין ולא ילין
מן הבשר,
V'lo yalin v'lo yalin
min habasar,
right, אשר תזבח בערב. asher tizbach ba'erev. Now how do we know
by the way that it's the 14th? Because it's תזבח בערב, tizbach
ba'erev, right, so what has to be שחט in the afternoon? The
only קרבן other than the פסח is חגיגת ארבעה עשר. chagigat arba'ah
asar. Okay, so there we know it's חגיגת י''ד. chagigat yud daled.
ולא ילין מן הבשר אשר תזבח בערב ביום הראשון אשר תזבח ביום
הראשון,
V'lo yalin min habasar asher tizbach ba'erev ba'yom ha'rishon
asher
tizbach ba'yom ha'rishon, that's right.
Anyway, אשר תזבח ביום הראשון asher tizbach ba'yom ha'rishon is another קרבן.
That's the חגיגה chagigah of the 15th, right? ביום הראשון עד בוקר,
Ba'yom ha'rishon ad boker, don't let that go over until the 16th.
So we have two פסוקים psukim here essentially. Don't let that sleep
over till the next morning and this is פסול pasul on the
15th, and the ביום הראשון קרבן, ba'yom ha'rishon korban, don't let that
go till that next morning till the 16th. So maybe the פסוק
pasuk is saying that each קרבן gets פסול pasul the next morning.
רישא Reisha is one פסוק pasuk and the other and the other
סיפא.
seifa. Exactly. Exactly. Okay. So now it says וזו לבוקרה וזו לבוקרה.
v'zu l'vokrah v'zu l'vokrah. הדר
אמר, Hadar amar, so maybe that's the way to read the פסוק
pasuk and that each one the 14th and the 15th חגיגה chagigah,
becomes פסול pasul the next morning. הדר אמר, Hadar amar, then it
says אלא דקיימא לן חגיגה נאכלת לשני ימים ולילה אחד, ela d'kayma
lan chagiga ne'echelet lishnei yamim v'laila echad,
but one minute, we have a principle, we know that there's at
least one חגיגה chagigah out there in the universe that's eaten for
two days and the intervening night. But if So if you say
both the 14th and the 15th חגיגה chagigah are פסול pasul in
the morning, those are all the חגיגות chagigas that exist in the
world, is the חגיגה of the 14th and the normal חגיגה of
יום טוב. So you can't, if you read this פסוק pasuk this
way, no חגיגה is כשר kasher for two days. And how do
we know that there's a חגיגה out there in the world
that is כשר kasher for only one day, I mean, that is
כשר kasher for two days? אם נדר או נדבה im neder o
nedava because we have this פסוק pasuk that speaks about a נדר
neder or נדבה nedava which is eaten for two days and we
understand that that includes a חגיגה. במאי? bemai? What type of, I
don't know, Rashi says it's because of the ב. be. What type
of חגיגה could this פסוק pasuk refer to? אי חגיגת ארבעה עשר
הכתיב בה יום ולילה. ei chagigat arba'ah asar haktiva beiyom velayla. If
it's the 14th, if we read the פסוק pasuk in that way,
that's only has day and a night. אי חגיגת טו הכתיב בה
יום ולילה. ei chagigat tet vav haktiva beiyom velayla. It's as that.
אלא האי לחגיגת טו והאי קרא לחגיגת ארבעה עשר. ela hai lechagigat
tet vav vehai kara lechagigat arba'ah asar. So what you have to
say is, since this would mean that there's no חגיגה that exists
for two days, we have to take off the 15th. We say
the 15th חגיגה, that's בסוף פסוק, besof pasuk, אם נדר, im neder,
okay? There we're going to move the 15th חגיגה and that tells
you, two days and a night, okay? And this whole פסוק pasuk
now is talking about the 14th. But if the whole פסוק pasuk
is talking about the 14th, right, we, the way now we're forced
to read it is to read it ביום הראשון bayom harishon now
means that you are, no, the 14th is still the 15th day,
the 14th קורבן, korban, but it's the 15th and we read that
you are זובח בערב ביום הראשון, zove'ach ba'erev bayom harishon, right, it's
only, it's, you're eating it on the 15th, and it only becomes
פסול עד בוקר ad boker until the following morning, the morning that
follows the 15th, which means the 16th. So as soon as you
move the 15th קורבן korban away and give that two days and
a night, then this פסוק also winds up teaching you that the
חגיגה of the 14th is two days, is two days because ביום
הראשון
bayom harishon now means that it's to continue to be eaten on
the 15th.
Okay? Question? Yes.
Not yet, let me finish this thought.
Okay, so the גמרא says, לימא חגיגת טו דנאכלת שני ימים ולילה
אחד. leima chagigat tet vav dene'echelet shnei yamim velayla echad. Now, now
we get back to what, how this is relevant to this discussion
before about the אימורים imurim running out at
night. So טעמא דכתב ביום הראשון לבוקר דמאי בוקר בוקר שני. ta'ama
dechtav bayom harishon laboker demai boker boker sheni. Now the only way
we know that בוקר boker here means that you have till the
16th, the second morning, is because ביום הראשון bayom harishon we understand
it's telling you that you can eat the 15th and בוקר boker
means the בוקר boker following ביום הראשון. bayom harishon. So you see
the only, we assume, the base point is we assume בוקר boker
means the immediate preceding morning, following morning, okay? And the only way
this means two mornings away from when you started was because we
introduced the idea that we're past the 15th, so בוקר boker means
the following morning. הא כל היכא דכתיב בוקר סתם בוקר ראשון, ha
kol heicha dechtiv boker stam boker rishon, so therefore any time it
סתם stam says בוקר, boker, בוקר ראשון boker rishon obviously means the
first morning, אף על גב דלא כתיב ביה ראשון, af al gav
delo ktiv beih rishon, even had you not had the special word
ראשון. Okay, so really a very simple point. What else would בוקר
boker mean if not the following morning? If it can mean the
second morning, it can mean the third morning. So at the bottom
line though, everybody disagrees with the הלכה. halacha. The הלכה halacha is
that you have two days to eat the meat, but the, when
it says לא
ילין עד בוקר lo yalin ad boker it means that the fats
have to be finished the following night, they do, they end before
the meat. And the reason is the fats are about the הקרבה.
hakrava. So the הקרבה hakrava is in the day, you have a
night to wrap it up and then it's over, no matter how
long you have to eat the meat. Okay, and here.